<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of a paper, presented to the General Assembly, October 1690 Containing the complaints of many Presbyterian people, living in several shyres of Scotland. And novv a second time vvith additions offered to their consideration.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A189A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223505</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896522</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896522</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133581</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75140)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133581)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2415:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of a paper, presented to the General Assembly, October 1690 Containing the complaints of many Presbyterian people, living in several shyres of Scotland. And novv a second time vvith additions offered to their consideration.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  General Assembly --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133581:1"/>
            <head>An Account of a <hi>PAPER,</hi> preſented to the <hi>GENERAL
ASSEMBLY, <hi>October</hi> 1690.</hi> Containing the <hi>Complaints</hi> of
many <hi>Presbyterian</hi> People, living in ſeveral Shyres of
<hi>Scotland.</hi> And novv a Second time vvith <hi>Additions</hi> offered to
their Conſideration.</head>
            <p>AS Union in Truth and Duty is a great Mercy and Bleſſing, and
ought carefully to be intertained and maintained, ſo Diviſion is alwayes to
be wearied of as a Miſery, and all lawful and honeſt Endeavours to be made
uſe of, for healing the Breach: Of both theſe, the Church of
<hi>Scotland</hi> hath been partaker in a great meaſure; Sometime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
this Church was famous for Union, and did ſhare of the Bleſſings, which
uſually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends ſuch a happy Condition; Nevertheleſs of late, ſhe hath
been much rent with Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and broken with Breaches, cauſed by the
ſad Defections and Back-ſlidings where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many of her Members, in the late
defyling and unhappy times were involved; Againſt which, we thought it our
duty to bear Witneſs and Teſtimony, by withdrawing from theſe, guilty of,
and defending the ſame, out of Love to them, and that they
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight be convinced and aſhamed
thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But albeit we did withdraw from many <hi>Presbyterian</hi>
Miniſters, (whom notwithſtanding we loved and reverenced) involved in, and
defending ſeveral of theſe Defections, ſeeing no other way left us in
that broken and confuſed ſtate, of freeing our ſelves, from partaking in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereof; yet we never owned or
looked upon it, as a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or the
Miniſtry thereof, or ſo ſtated it, as that we would never more Unite: For
as alwiſe we declared our willingneſs to joyn again, when ever we could
have the opportunity without Sin; So of late we gave a demonſtration thereof,
in applying to the <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> by offering to them a
<hi>Paper,</hi> containing our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,</hi> which we earneſtly
deſired might be Heard and Redreſſed, that ſo our Union after ſo long
an interruption, might be the more comfortable. A brief account of the
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of which <hi>Paper</hi> followeth.</p>
            <p>When it was known, that there would be an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi>
it was judged requiſite, we ſhould lay hold upon that opportunity to
remonſtrate and repreſent to them our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> and
<hi>Grievances</hi> (under which we had been groaning) and ſeek Redreſs of
the ſame, and that theſe Defections and Corruptions might be condemned,
which had offended us, and cauſed our withdrawing in the broken Caſe
foreſaid, that ſo our Union might be with the greater comfort. Upon which a
<hi>Paper</hi> being drawn up, it was brought to one of our <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Meetings,</hi> where it was agreed, to the End all our Friends concerned
therein might be throughly informed of the ſaid <hi>Paper,</hi> that Coppies
ſhould be written and ſhown to our Societies, who might conſider thereof,
and ſend two or three, or moe of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber unto <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to
Subſcrive it in their Name. According to which concluſion, ſome
Perſons, from ſeveral places of the Countrey, came to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi>
where the <hi>Paper</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by ſundry Hands, in name of many others. The Tenor whereof
followeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:133581:2"/>
               <head>To the MODERATOR, and Remnant Members of this Reverend
GENERAL ASSEMBLY.</head>
               <head type="sub">The COMPLAINTS and Humble PETITION of many
<hi>Presbyterian</hi> People, Living in ſeveral Shyres of
<hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEEing the Lord in the riches of His infinite Mercy, wherein He
hath abounded towards this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in the late Revolution of Providence,
far beyond all poſſible Acknowledgements, hath been pleaſed to grant at
length this long wanting, long wiſhed and prayed for Priviledge, of ſeeing
a free <hi>General Aſſembly</hi> of Presbyterian Miniſters, gathered and
fenced in the Name of our Lord JESUS; We cannot, dare not, and muſt not omitt
this Opportunity of Applying our ſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, for a Redreſs of
theſe many long laſting <hi>Complaints</hi> and <hi>Grievances,</hi> under
which we have Groaned theſe many years; The chiefeſt, bittereſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
moſt burdenſome of which (thô we have not wanted our ſhare of other
Burdens and Afflictions very heavy) hath been, and yet remains to be, even in
this plenty, our ſcarcity and famine of <hi>Goſpel Ordinances,</hi> wherein
we have languiſhed of a long time, ſighing over our ſilent Sabbaths, as
Sheep ſcattered without a Shepherd fainting for hunger, at the head of every
Street, and panting after the green Paſtures and pleaſant Water-brooks of
the Preached Goſpel; And yet ſcarred and made to ſtand aloof from it, by
the Stumblings, Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Defections and Diviſions of theſe unhappy
times paſt; Which, as it hath been our greateſt ſorrow, ſo no comfort
on this ſide Heaven, could be ſo deſireable, as to re-enjoy and recover
again acceſs with clearneſs to pure and powerful <hi>Goſpel
Ordinances,</hi> without which we ſhall never have a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant day in the
greateſt abundance of all our outward peace. It was truely, <hi>Right
Reverend</hi> a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon us moſt heavy to bear, that we were called
Deſpiſers of the Goſpel, and of the Miniſtry thereof, which ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo far as we had clearneſs and acceſs, we ſought
after and followed, even upon the hazard of our Lives, ſo earneſtly, that
no terror of Perſecuters could drive us from the purſute of it: And nothing
moved us to withdraw from theſe Miniſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who reckoned themſelves
rejected by us (whom nevertheleſs we loved and reſpected, and do high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> love and reverence) but their ſad
Involvements in the Defections of the late defyling and unhappy times; ſeeing
no other may left us in that broken ſtate, of keeping up a Teſtimony
againſt the ſame, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our
ſelves from partaking in the ſix thereof, but that abſtraction in theſe
circumſtances, which we never looked upon, as a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Reformed
&amp; covenanted Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (as is more fully ſhewed in our
<hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matory Vindication,</hi> which we here Homologate) but only from the
Defections &amp; Sins of which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of her Members were guilty; and not that
we ſhould never <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite more upon any Conditions: For Schiſm is, and ever
was equally hateful to us as ſinful <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion; and we are now, and alwiſe
were, moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireous to Joyn again, in terms moſt pleaſing to the
LORD, edifying to the Church, and ſatisfying to our Conſciences. We are not
for impoſing Terms, giving Directions, or preſcribing Rules to
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, more than we are to be impoſed upon, and implicitely led by
them; yet ſeeing People are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of the LORD, ſometimes in ſobriety,
to ſay to <hi>Archippus, Take heed to the Miniſtry, which thou haſt
received in the LORD, and fulfill it;</hi> And when Offences are given by
Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, it is Peoples Priviledge to plead for the removing of them, in a
Chriſtian way, to the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the offended Party. We humbly
conceive, in order to the removal of the many offences given and taken, in this
our day, in order to our comfortable Reconciliation together, and that we may
be reconciled to the LORD, and His Wrath turned away, that Confeſſing,
Foreſaking and Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Courſes that have been ſo offenſive, is
very neceſſary And ſeing in merciful Providence, there is a Door opened,
whereby ye have acceſs and capacity to fall about Building the Temple of the
Lord, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:133581:2"/>&amp; cleanſing it from theſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>neſſes, wherewith in times of
Defection bygone, it hath been defiled, and removing theſe Stumbling-blocks
which have offended the Conſciences of many tender and ſerious People:
Therefore, in all Humility and Reverance, we muſt take the freedom to
repreſent to this Reverend <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> in a few particulars, what
things chiefly have ſtumbled us, and occaſioned our withdrawing for ſo
long a time, from many Miniſters of this Church, which we cannot omit to
<hi>Complian</hi> of and <hi>Proteſt</hi> againſt: Deſigning hereby not
to irritate or offend, nor to lay the Faults of any open unto the World, nor to
plead our own Innocence, but deſiring to acknowledge our deep ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
alſo to the Sins, which hath provocked the LORD to all this anger againſt
this Church and Kingdom: That which hath drawn from us, the mentioning of
theſe things, is that the remembering of them, may help us all to the ſight
and ſenſe of theſe Sins amongſt others, that we may be found Mourning
for them, and keeping up a Teſtimony againſt them; And to ſhew our
earneſt deſire of having Peace and Truth, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Order, among all the
Lovers and Well wiſhers of Zion, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled upon Laſting and Solid
Foundations and Comfortable Communion in Ordinances reſtored to us who have
been long driven away, from that Benefite, by theſe offences.</p>
               <p>As it was not a little afflicting to behold, ſo it is now no
pleaſure to remember, that when <hi>Prelacy,</hi> condemned in the Word of
GOD, and abjured by our Covenants, was eſtabliſhed, many Miniſters did
hear and joyn with theſe perjured Hyrlings and Intruders the <hi>Prelats</hi>
and their <hi>Curats,</hi> Yea and perſwaded others to the like Practice:
Whereby their hands were ſtrengthened, and the Hearts of many of the Godly
were ſadned, and their Conſciences ſtumbled: We deſire to be thankful
that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie is condemned by Act of Parliament, nevertheleſs we are grieved
that ſuch Joyning and Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therewith is not yet condemned, nor the
Practiſe of theſe that withdrew approved.</p>
               <p>As it was no ſmal grief of heart to ſee the
<hi>Supremacy,</hi> which belongs only to the Lord JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, as King and Head of
His Church, given away to a miſerable Mortal, and ſettled upon him by Law;
ſo it was an augmentation to our Sorrow, to ſee an <hi>Indulgence</hi>
flowing therefrom, clogged with Reſtrictions, very prejudicial to the honour
and freedom of Chriſts Ambaſſadours, embraced by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Miniſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and juſtified by others, which did much ſtrengthen
theſe wicked <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations on our Lords Crown Rights, &amp; His Churches
Liberties, and gave occaſion of great Stumbling and Offence, and was a Bone
of Contention among the Lords People in this Land. But yet thô both the
accurſed Fountain, and impure Stream be removed and cut off, for which we
deſire to Bleſs the Lord, the Sin thereof nevertheleſs is not
Confeſſed and Condemned; the doing whereof we are perſwaded, would be
very contributive to the turning away of the Lords anger, and ſatisfying all
offended.</p>
               <p>It was very Stumbling and Offenſive to us, when many Snares
and Tentations were abounding and going through the Land, that then many
Miniſters who ſhould have Preached in Seaſon, and out of Seaſon, and
whom no Diſpenſation could diſcharge from that great and neceſſary
Duty, did not ſet the Trumpet to their mouth, to give faithful warning in
times of ſuch danger, as became Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; but thô often called to
Preach in the Countrey, did either faintly leave the Land, or lurked and lay by
in the Land, and others when they Preached, either did not apply their Doctrine
to the Times, ſo as we might take it up, or were ambiguous in their
Application of their Doctrine to the dangers of the Times, whereby many were
left to periſh in their iniquity, and the hands of theſe who endeavoured to
keep clean Garments, were not ſtrengthned: Yea, it was very offenſive to
behold the practice and carriage of ſome Miniſters, who inſtead of
ſtrengthning their hands, who were at that time moſt forwardlie and
zealouſlie appearing and contending for the Cauſe and Intereſt of CHRIST,
and joyning with, countenancing or encouraging the Miniſters, who were
Valiant for the Truth, and <pb n="4" facs="tcp:133581:3"/>Jeoparded their Lives, in the high
places of the fields, for the Teſtimony of CHRIST, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their
laudable endeavours, and reproached them, and their actings and ſufferings,
both at home and abroad.</p>
               <p>More eſpecialy it was ſad and ſtumbling to us, when many
<hi>Miſchiefs,</hi> were framed into Laws, by a Throne of Iniquity, when many
wicked <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Bonds,</hi> enſnaring Conſciences, contrare
to the Word of GOD, and our National Covenants were impoſed, and when we were
required upon pain of Death, to owne the Authority of, and acknowledge
Alegiance to <hi>Tyrants</hi> and <hi>Uſurpers,</hi> as our Lawful
Magiſtrats, whom GOD had ſet over us, as His Miniſters of Juſtice, that
then many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, did comply with theſe wicked Laws, and taught the
People to obey them, and ſome did take and ſubſcribe theſe
<hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Bonds</hi> themſelves, and perſwaded People to take
them, and not only owned and acknowledged Alegiance to theſe <hi>Tyrants</hi>
and <hi>Uſurpers,</hi> prayed for them and their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and pleaded for
the Lawfulneſs of their Authority; Yea, ſome prayed for the pretended
Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> But inſtead of ſympathizing with the ſufferings
of theſe that could not in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence owne that Authooity, condemned and
inveighed againſt them as fools, and dying in an errour. We have reaſon to
be thankful for this reviving in our Bondage, and that the yoke of
Oppreſſion and Perſecution is taken from off our necks; yet we wiſh
that untender carriage towards conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sufferers were reſented, and
the Heads and Cauſes were approven and juſtified, upon which theſe
reproached Martyrs and Confeſſors ſuffered.</p>
               <p>It was very burdenſome to our Conſciences, that a Popiſh
<hi>Toleration</hi> deſigned to introduce <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> into this Land
again, granted by K. <hi>James</hi> from his Abſolute Power, which he
blaſphemouſlie arrogated to himſelf, and whereby he preſumed to ſtop
the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with many
Limitations, was embraced by many <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters, and
Addreſſed for, to that Popiſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper, in the Name of <hi>ALL:</hi>
Which many of the Godly of the Land looked upon with weeping eyes, as a ſad
ſtep of Defection from the wonted Zeal of the Miniſters of
<hi>Scotland;</hi> The Sin and Scandal of this courſe is evident in a
<hi>Teſtimony</hi> given in againſt the ſame, by ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
which we here own: Yet now, notwithſtanding that it be removed, and the
wicked power it flowed from, we cannot think the Sin and Scandal of it is taken
away, ſo long as the ſame is not confeſſed, mourned over and
condemned.</p>
               <p>The condemning of all theſe <hi>Courſes</hi> of
<hi>Complyance</hi> and <hi>Defections,</hi> would not only be as a Beacon
ſet up to hinder the following Generation from ſpliting on ſuch dangerous
Rocks, but alſo will make our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting and Joyning with theſe, from whom
we ſtand at a diſtance (which we long for, and pray for) cordial and
comfortable.</p>
               <p>We are alſo diſſatisfied and offended at ſeveral things
at preſent; It might have been expected, that the Mercies we have met with of
late, ſhould have filled our Hearts with kindly ſorrow for our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Sins
and Backſliding, and inflamed the Souls of all the Lovers of Chriſt, with
more Zeal, for advancing and promoting Reformation in this Land, according to
the capacity and opportunity the Lord hath put in their hands; But alas!
unſuteable hath been our Returns of Fruitfulneſs and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; And
as all of us have come far ſhort of improving theſe Opportunities, ſo the
practice of theſe Miniſters continues to be very offenſive and
ſtumbling, who inſtead of Confeſſing and Condemning the above written
Defections, and minding the People of their former Backſlidings, and
diſcovering the Sins of the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
times, that were many and heinous, to the end, they may be induced to mourn
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and to turn unto the Lord, do yet continue to defend and hide their
own guilt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to harden others in Impenitency; So that the wrongs
done to Chriſt, are like to be forgotten and buried, and few are like to be
brought off from the evil of their vvayes.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:133581:3"/>
               <p>We are alſo much diſcouraged and diſſatisfied, that the
<hi>National</hi> and <hi>Solemn League</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants,</hi> have not
only not been renewed, but not contended for by many, the affront done to them,
and their binding force not declared, but like to be buried in oblivion. And
more eſpecially it was wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear, that when opportunitie was
given, and acceſs to Addreſs the King and Parliament, the mentioning of
theſe holy Covenants was omitted; And ſince the King and Queen were
advanced to the Throne, we fear that that faithfulneſs &amp; freedom hath not
been uſed as was wont to be in former times, to warne and admoniſh their
Majeſties, of the Sins and Snares of the Throne, to beware of evil
Councellors, and of the guilt and danger of tampering with, and patronizing
<hi>Prelacie</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor to diſcover
and declare to them, and the Parliament, the Sin and danger of bringing into,
and keeping in places of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower and
Truſt, in Judicatories and <hi>Armies,</hi> Perſon's who are known
Malignant Enemies to Truth and Godlineſs, and to the preſent Intereſt now
to be maintained, as faithful Miniſters in former times uſed to witneſs
againſt ſuch ſinful Aſſociations; and after all that is come upon us
for our evil deeds, and have gotten ſuch a deliverance as this, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain His
Commandements be broken, by joyning in affinity with the People of theſe
abominations, it will be more than ever dangerous both to King and Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, albeit we dare not deſpiſe the day of ſmall
things, and deſires to bleſs the Lord for what we have ſeen; yet we
cannot conceal our ſorrow, that the great and glorious <hi>Attainments</hi>
between the year <hi>1638</hi> &amp; <hi>1649,</hi> being years of the right
Hand of the Moſt High in which we were brought under the renewed Bond of
Solemn <hi>Covenants,</hi> are not revived, nor any honourable mention made of
them, in any of the Acts, eſtabliſhing the Priviledges of the Church, which
we think a loſing of the ground which our Fathers gained. We do not ſay,
that it was in the power of Miniſters to redreſs this, before or after, it
was done; yet as we conceive the pleading for the full of this in their
<hi>Addreſſes,</hi> was not above their reach, and that they ſhould have
ſignified their diſlike at the want thereof, and taken what they got by
theſe Acts, with a Proteſtation, that it ſhould be without prejudice of
their ſeeking and getting more; ſo in our poor Judgement, we think in all
Eſtabliſhments of Religion and religious Rights in a Land, reſpect, is
alwayes to be had to the Patern and Rule of GOD's revealed Will in His Word,
and not to Worldly Politicks.</p>
               <p>It is alſo very diſcouraging and offenſive, and we cannot
but complain of it, that now when there is an opportunity to purge the Church
from theſe Corruptions, wherewith ſhe hath been long peſtered and
plagued; yet thô <hi>Prelacy</hi> be aboliſhed by the <hi>State,</hi>
and many <hi>Curats</hi> put away, ſome one way, ſome another, we hear of
none cenſured and removed for <hi>Prelacy, Perjurie</hi> and
<hi>Intruſion,</hi> and ſome Miniſters are alſo pleading for keeping
them in, upon Carnal and Politick grounds, who we fear may afterwards do more
Hurt and Miſchief, than the Good now pretended can countervail; And that if
this occaſion be loſt of purging the Church of inſufficient, corrupt and
ſcandalous Officers of all ſorts, eſpecially of <hi>Prelatick
Curats,</hi> and of planting it with Godly, faithful, and able Miniſters, we
may all repent of it too late.</p>
               <p>More eſpecially, It is very ſtumbling and offenſive to us,
that albeit there be an opportunity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear and danger to exerciſe
Diſcipline impartially and faithfully; yet ſome who have formerly taken the
abominable <hi>Teſt,</hi> and are guilty of other groſs <hi>Scandals,</hi>
are admitted to be Officers of the Church, ſome to be Miniſters, and ſome
to be Elders, and many guilty of very groſs degrees of Complyance, are
admitted to the Sacrament, without any publick Acknowledgement of their
Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; <pb n="6" facs="tcp:133581:4"/>whereby they and others are hardened, and many of
the Godly ſtumbled, to the great diſadva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Church.</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>Right Reverend,</hi> we expect and intreat,
that ye will not offend at our freedom, in what we here <hi>Repreſent,</hi>
but our meaning and end to have differences ſatisfyingly removed, will move
you, to put a favourable conſtruction upon that, which a Critical
Diſpoſition, might be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to cenſure for raſhneſs and ignorance,
and medling in matters wherein we are not concerned: But tho we ſhould be
condemned and cenſured with the greateſt ſeverity, and be counted yet
more vile, we muſt ſeek, we muſt cry, for the removing of theſe
<hi>Stumbling Blocks,</hi> and condemning theſe <hi>Courſes,</hi> which
have done our Lord <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> ſo much wrong, and His Children ſo much
hurt, in the ſtanding in the way of their comfortable and edifying Communion
with the Church; Let the famiſhing and ſtarving caſe of our Souls,
through want of the Bleſſed <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and our hungering to hear it
preached by you, prevail with you to conſider our <hi>Complaints,</hi> and
let the Wounds of our bleeding Mother, panting to be healed by the Hand of the
tender hearted <hi>Phyſician,</hi> have weight with you not to ſlight or
deſpiſe our <hi>Deſires:</hi> But if ye ſhall ſhut your eyes and ears
at them, then we know at the time, no Remedy left us, but to <hi>Complain</hi>
and <hi>Proteſt</hi> unto <hi>Judicatories;</hi> and cry, ſigh and groan to
the <hi>Father of Mercies,</hi> who is tender of all His Litle ones, and is the
Hearer of Prayer, that He may ſee to it, and heal our Backſlidings and
Breaches in His own time and way, and not lay it to your charge, that ye have
had ſo little regard to the ſtumbling and ſaddenning of ſo many of His
poor, broken, bruiſed, and ſcattered Sheep, and that ye have not had
greater care to ſtrengthen the Diſeaſed, and to heal that which was
ſick, and to bind up that which was broken, and to bring again that which was
driven away, and to ſeek that which was loſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AFter Subſcribing of the</hi> Paper, <hi>ſome Men were
choſen in name of the reſt, to preſent it to the</hi> Aſſembly,
<hi>to deſire an Anſwer, and to uſe diligence therein, of which they were
to give an account to their Friends: But the delivering of it in was thought
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to be delayed a little until it was known, what would be done with
a</hi> Paper <hi>given in to the</hi> Aſſembly <hi>by Mr</hi> Thomas
Lining, <hi>Mr</hi> Alexander Sheilds, <hi>and Mr</hi> William Boyd; <hi>yet
thô it be not expedient to relate either the iſue of that buſineſs,
or how the ſame was managed, nevertheleſs it is not unſuitable to the
preſent purpoſe to mention this, that inſtead of a ſatisfactory
Anſwer, it was very offenſive to many, that the</hi> Aſſembly <hi>by
a</hi> Vote <hi>refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to read the foreſaid</hi> Paper <hi>preſented by
the Miniſters above named, upon the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons given in by the</hi> Committee
<hi>of</hi> Overtures, <hi>why it ſhould not be read, which condemned the
ſame, before it was heard; eſpecially the perſons entruſted with the
ſubſcribing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving of our</hi> Paper, <hi>and ſome others were
ſo offended, that they judged it duty to ſignifie their diſſatisfaction
therewith to the</hi> Aſsembly: <hi>Whereupon a ſhort</hi> Paper <hi>being
drawn up, was ſubſcribed by the Men (choſen to deliver the other</hi>
Paper) <hi>in their own Name; Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting it as an additional</hi>
Complaint, <hi>that the</hi> Aſſembly <hi>had, in the manner above
ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, refuſed to read the foreſaid</hi> Paper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To get opportunity for delivering in both theſe</hi>
Papers <hi>to the</hi> Committee <hi>of</hi> Overtures, <hi>by whom they might
be tranſmitted to the whole</hi> Aſſembly, <hi>the Men went to the place
where the ſaid</hi> Committee <hi>was ſitting, where meeting with two
Miniſters (Members thereof) and after ſome conference with them, concerning
the</hi> Papers; <hi>One of the Miniſters ſaid, he would inform the</hi>
Committee <hi>of them; Accordingly they having both gone in, acquainted 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133581:4"/>the</hi> Committee <hi>therewith, who (inſtead of giving
the Men acceſs, a priviledge denied to none but them) only nominate two
Miniſters and a Ruling Elder, to ſpeak with them: Theſe immediatly coming
out, had conference with the Men: Before whom firſt the ſhort</hi> Paper,
<hi>next the Larger were read; After hearing both, and deſiring ſome things
to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in the large</hi> Paper <hi>(which could not be condeſcended
unto) they endeavoured to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Men from preſſing the reading
of them in the</hi> Aſſembly; <hi>which the Men inſiſted earneſtly
for, and for an Anſwer to return to their Friends: When theſe Miniſters
found them ſo preſſing for this, they promiſed to repreſent it to
the</hi> Committee; <hi>whereupon one of them went in, ſpoke of it to them,
and delivered the</hi> Papers <hi>to the</hi> Clerk. <hi>After this, the Men at
ſeveral occaſions, ſolicited the Miniſters above mentioned, and ſome
others, that the</hi> Papers <hi>might be read in the</hi> Aſſembly,
<hi>and to have ſomewhat to return to their Friends: But the Anſwer they
received, was a</hi> Letter <hi>ſubſcribed by three Miniſters, direct to
them: Which followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Loving Friends,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THE <hi>Papers</hi> you gave in to the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi>
were firſt given in to the <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Overtures,</hi> and we
were by them appointed to confer with you; And after ſome conference with
you, we moved in the <hi>Committee,</hi> that the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> would
order the <hi>Papers</hi> to be given in to theſe, who were to draw up the
<hi>Monitory Letter,</hi> and cauſes of the <hi>Faſt,</hi> that they might
make their own uſe thereof, in drawing up the ſame: Which at the firſt
next <hi>Seſſion</hi> of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> on Saturnday laſt,
the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> was accordingly done in open
<hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and we by the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> allowed to report
the ſame to you; which now accordingly we do: And we hope this will
ſatisfie you, and others who did commiſſionate you; and that the Lord
will encline your Hearts to Peace, and to guard againſt any further rent in
the Church of GOD; and in this hope we ſubſcribe our ſelves,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 3. 1690,</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Friends and Servants in the
LORD.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRom which</hi> Letter, <hi>we ſhall only take notice of
this, that as we have never yet ſeen the</hi> Monitory Letter <hi>mentioned
therein, whereby we do not know what uſe is made in it of our</hi> Paper;
<hi>ſo albeit we have got a ſight of the Cauſes of the</hi> Faſt,
<hi>from which it was ſaid (ſeveral times) that we ſhould receive
Satisfaction to our Scruples, yet we are ſo far from getting of the ſame,
that we muſt Complain, not only of the ambiguity of ſome Expreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in
it, but alſo of its Lameneſs, ſeveral things being omitted, which are
ſteps of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and Cauſes of Wrath; And that the abominable</hi>
Teſt, Declaration, Prelatical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſions, <hi>being once in, were put out
again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We hope, as well as Seriouſly deſires, that our deſign
in Publiſhing what is above, may not be miſtaken, but rightly
Conſtructed, ſeeing it is not to irritate or offend any Perſon; But to
make manifeſt what hath been our endeavours, in order to get a</hi>
Comfortable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, <hi>with theſe Miniſters, from whom we are yet
ſtanding at a diſtance: As alſo to let them know, how unexpected, yea
aſtoniſhing it was to us, when we heard that our</hi> Paper <hi>of</hi>
Complaints, <hi>was ſo little regarded, as not once to be read, either in
the</hi> Committee, <hi>or open</hi> Aſſembly; <hi>It contained what really
was and is ground of offence and matter of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to us; And whatever was
pretended for not reading thereof, yet the Conſequences <pb n="8" facs="tcp:133581:5"/>hath been ſad, having created Jealouſies, Scruples and
Diſcontents, and hath been tho occaſion of a further rent, for it could not
be rationally expected, that to deny that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to them, which was
granted to others, was the way to heal the breach, which was wide, and remove
the Scruples that were many, of theſe, who are Conſciencious; This was
rather the way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oment new Debates
and Jarrs, then to cement, or remove the old: And in like manner that we may
have opportunity and occaſion hereby, again to deſire of, and cry unto
Miniſters, not only for removing of our former Scruples, and redreſſing
of our old</hi> Complaints <hi>and</hi> Grievances, <hi>but alſo to</hi>
Repreſent, <hi>ſome</hi> New Ones, <hi>which are not only burdenſome,
grievous and offenſive to us, but to many of the Godly in the Land;
earneſtly intreating, and fervently deſiring, that Miniſters, may do what
is incumbent for them, and in their Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for removing of the ſame: One
is,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Admiſſion <hi>of ſome of the</hi> Prelatical
Curats, <hi>not only to the exerciſe of the Miniſtry, but to a ſhare of
the Government of this Church; of which, we crave leave to ſignifie our
diſlike and diſſatisfaction, and to teſtify againſt the Peſtering
and polluting the Church with them; In regard it is the receiving in of ſuch
Men whom the Scriptures declares ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided and with drawn from,
becauſe they have cauſed diviſions and offences, contrare to the Doctrine
which this Church learned, and walked not only diſorderly themſelves, but
many of them compelled others to do ſo, and Perſecuted theſe who
deſired to keep their Garments clean; In regard it is unreaſonable, and not
conſiſtent with policy, to put Weapones in the Hands of</hi> Enemies,
<hi>leſt they may turn them againſt us, if not openly, yet in a way as
dangerous; Yea it is not long ſince all of them were Reckoned</hi> Such:
<hi>And whatever ſome of them pretend to now, yet the time of this Change
makes the ſincerity of their Repentance ſtrongly ſuſpicious, neither
does it ſeem reaſonable or ſafe to admit ſuch Men to a ſhare of the
Government, who oppoſed the ſame, while Power was in their Hands, or to
commit to them the care of Souls, who formerly have poiſoned and done great
hurt to many of them; In regard they are incapable to give ſecurity, for
their being Faithful, and true to the Government, as is required in the
Inſtructions given by the</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, <hi>being Men, not only guilty
of Intruſion, dreadful Apoſtacy, advancing the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Satan,
perſecution (ſome one way, ſome another) of the Godly, and not a few of
them, of profanity and errour, but alſo of groſs perjurie by taking wicked
and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory</hi> Oaths, <hi>as that abominable</hi> Teſt <hi>&amp;c.
And teaching others to do ſo, all repugnant to our</hi> Solemn Covenants,
<hi>whereby they have forefaulted the Honour of any</hi> Truſt <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
Honeſt Men, much more in ſuch great and weighty matters, as are the having
a ſhare in the Government of CHRISTS Houſe, and the care and over-ſight
of Souls; In regard the taking in of theſe Men, will tend to the preſent
hurt of the Church, ſeing it will occaſion a great Breach and Diviſion in
the ſame, which will do much more hurt, than all the good theſe Men will
do, can countervail; In regard it will rend to the prejudice of the
Poſterity, whoſe advantage ſhould be ſought, by endeavouring to
tranſmit pure Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances to them, which we think cannot well be done, and
thoſe preſerved entire, if theſe Men be entruſted with the
diſpenſing of them: For as they are known formerly to be of corrupt
Principles and Practices themſelves, and the ſoundneſs of the Change,
that they make, conſidering the time thereof (beſide other things) being
greatly to be feared, ſo they will endeavour by degrees to bring in others of
the ſame Stamp, whereby at length (others dying) a little Leaven may leaven
the whole Lump, and ſo the ordinances be in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being corrupted,
if not Changed, which will tend to the unſpeakable diſadvantage 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133581:5"/>of the Poſterity: And in regard it will tend to the hurt of
theſe Men themſelves, ſeing to admit them to ſuch a great Truſt, ſo
eaſily and haſtily may harden them in their former evil wayes; whereas a
more ſtrict and ſharp dealing, according as the rules of Diſcipline
preſcribes to take with ſuch ſcandalous perſons, might by the
Bleſſing of the LORD bring them to a ſight and conviction of the ſame.
Theſe, and many other reaſons that might be adduced, have weight with us;
and we are hopeful will ſo far prevail with Miniſters as to withſtand and
oppoſe (now when they have power and opportunity) the polluting and
peſtering the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and any mixing with the Men of theſe
Abominations, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what</hi> Authority <hi>may enjoyn: But if
it ſhall be otherwayes, as it will preſage ſad things to this poor Church
and Kingdom, ſo it will give ground of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mbling at others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In like manner, as it is offenſive and ſtumbling to us,
that ſome Miniſters and Elders hath been admitted to be conſtituent
Members of the</hi> Aſsembly, <hi>who are ſo heinouſly guiltie and were
ſo deeply involved in the defections of the late defyling times, as by the
Word of GOD, and Conſtititutions of this Church, would debar them; So it
cannot but be more ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and is mater of Complaint, that albeit there
were many Reverend and Worthy</hi> Divines <hi>in the</hi> Aſſembly
<hi>and</hi> Commiſſion <hi>thereof, yet oft times, when they have had
publick matters to manage, and ſome things to put in Print, that ſuch
ſhould have been appointed for that end, who are laxeſt, and deeply
involved in that late defections; The ſad effects and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences whereof
appears already, and certainly will be more evident afterwards, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
by that Book Intituled A</hi> ſecond Vindication of the Church of Scotland
&amp;c. <hi>Wherein the Author (who was emploied for drawing up thereof, and
does it name of the whole) not only gives ignominious Characters and Epithets
unto Honeſt and Conſciencious Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but alſo condemns and
diſownes their laudable actings in eaſing the Church and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in
the</hi> Interregnum, <hi>of theſe perjured hirelings and intruders, the</hi>
Curats: <hi>Wherein we are concerned in it, we are ſo far from being a
ſhamed thereof, that we ſtand not to let it be known, that we are chiefly
ſorry, we were not more active; And we may adventure with ſome confidence
to ſay the like in behalf of others: And in ſome ſingleneſs of heart
may add, that what we did therein, was from a Principle of Conſcience, and as
a Duty lying bound on us, and not (meerly) becauſe they were our
Perſecuters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another thing offenſive to us and many others, is the
ſeldom mentioning of our</hi> National and Solemn Covenants, <hi>not only in
Preaching, but at Baptizing of Children, at which time formerly it was uſual
to mention them, but now by ſome only darkly hinted at, and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
altogether laid aſide; And it cannot but be grievous and wounding unto us,
that the Author of the foreſaid Book, ſhould inſinuat ſo much as it is
concluded, ſo be done. We are not for giving directions unto Miniſters;
Nevertheleſs, we humbly conceive, we may ſafely complain of the ſilence
of many of them, in this, eſpecially, when it is like to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch
ſad and lamentable effects, as the wearing out (among many) of the ſenſe
and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the obligation and binding force of theſe</hi>
Covenants, <hi>and that not a few are like to forget, that the ſame hath been
broken and burnt in this Land. Whatever difficulties are alleaged, hindering
the Solemn Renovations of them at this time, yet Miniſters may even at this
ſeaſon, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w people that
perjurie and breach of Covenant, are among the ſins of the Land, and what way
all ranks are guiltie of the ſame, as alſo that theſe Covenants 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133581:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>are ſtill binding, and the obligation of them
remains inviolable, notwithſtanding of any iniquious Law made againſt them
in the late unhappy times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Like as, it is offenſive to us, and many others, that
Miniſters hath been ſo ſilent at the</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments <hi>already made
upon the priviledges of this Church, in putting a ſtope in a great:
Meaſure, to the purging out of the</hi> Epiſcopal Clergy; <hi>by which
Reformation is hindered, and negligent, erroneous, inſufficient and
ſcandalous men are ſtill kept in: As alſo their ſilence at the
adjournment of the</hi> General Aſſembly <hi>by proclamation, whereby that
Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Court is made like one of the civil Judicatories of the
Nation: Theſe Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Uſurpations (againſt which we, for our
parts; cannot but</hi> Witneſs <hi>and</hi> Proteſt) <hi>makes us afraid of
the plague of</hi> Eraſtianſim <hi>(of which we heartily wiſh we may be
diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed) the beginings whereof, and the very appearance of a Supremacie
over the Church of CHRIST, arrogate by King or Council, or any whomſoever;
Miniſters eſpecially, ought to withſtand, and not be hindered from
aſſerting the priviledges of His Houſe, either for the terrour,
pleaſure or perſwaſion of any Mortal, high or low, great or
ſmall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To conclude; That it may be manifeſt for what end we
mention theſe things (which is not fom pleaſure to ſpeak of them, or to
make a noiſe about them, but from a fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have them
redreſſed and removed) and that all concerned, may know how deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous we
are of</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion <hi>in the Lord, and what longing we have for the
benefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Goſpel in purity
and power; Again and again we earneſtly intreate and ſeriouſly
beſeeches that theſe our</hi> Complaints <hi>and</hi> Grivances <hi>above,
may be laid to heart, and that ſome effectual, way may be fallen upon to
remove and take them away, which we long for, that ſo our</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<hi>may be more comfortable, and we expect the Bleſſing of the Lord
thereupon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
